<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>

<preface id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        The DAO pattern (Data Access Object) used to be one of the core J2EE patterns and could be found in most 
        enterprise applications reading and writing data to persistent stores. While the Java Persistence API (JPA) 
        as part of Java EE 5+ has replaced many aspects of the DAO pattern, it is still a good approach to centralize
        complex query logic related to specific entities.
    </para>
    <para>
        The CDI Query module is intended to help you simplifying your DAO layer. While you will have complex queries
        in a DAO requiring your full attention, there will also be many simple ones often requiring repetitive code and
        cluttering your DAO. This is where the CDI query module will help you keeping your DAO lean so you can focus
        on the though things. The code sample below will give you a quick overview on the common usage scenarios of the
        CDI Query module:
    </para>
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public abstract PersonDao extends AbstractEntityDao<Person, Long> {

    @Query("select p from Person p where p.ssn = ?1")
    public abstract Person findBySSN(String ssn);
    
    @Query(named=Person.BY_FULL_NAME)
    public abstract Person findByFullName(String firstName, String lastName);
    
    public abstract List<Person> findByAgeBetweenAndGender(int minAge, int maxAge, Gender gender);

}]]></programlisting>
    <para>
        As you see in the sample, there are several usage scenarios outlined here:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                Create an unimplemented method which automatically executes a given JPQL query string with parameters.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Create an unimplemented method which automatically executes a named query with parameters.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Create a method which executes a query by a method expression and its parameters. 
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        The details on how to use those features are outlines in the following chapters.
    </para>
    
</preface>